Guide to the James Hester Clippings Collection MC.149
New York University Archives
James Hester Clippings Collection
1911-1974
1960-1973
New York University Archives
New York University. Office of University Development and Alumni Relations
MC.149
1 linear foot in 2 manuscript boxes
James McNaughton Hester served at New York University (NYU) as Dean of the Graduate School of Arts and Science and Executive Dean of Arts and Sciences from 1960-1961, and as University President from 1962-1975. The James Hester Clippings Collection contains newspaper clippings, inauguration proceedings, NYU press releases, correspondence with Ralph Nader, selected writings such as reports, proposals and articles, biographical information for Marquis Who's Who and one Association of American Colleges publication all related to the NYU and post-NYU career of James Hester.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This collection is derived from biographical files from the Office of Development. The collection was sent to the University Archives along with approximately 1,000 other biographical files of former University employees in March of 1997.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged chronologically and by format into two series:
I. Clippings
II. Press Releases
Biographical Note
James M. Hester was born in Chester, Pennsylvania, on April 19, 1924, to James Montgomery and Margaret (McNaughton) Hester. Hester received his diploma from Woodrow Wilson High School in Long Beach, California, in 1942 and graduated with a Bachelor of Arts, summa cum laude in the humanities and magna cum laude in history, from Princeton University in 1945.
Hester served as a civil information and education officer with a military government team in the Fukuoka district of Japan following graduation and later obtained a Rhodes scholarship to attend Pembroke College of Oxford University, where he received a Bachelor of Arts in 1950. Hester also received his Master of Arts with second class honors in Philosophy, Politics and Economics in 1953 and Doctor of Philosophy in International Affairs in 1955 from Oxford University.
In 1957 Hester became Provost of Long Island University's Brooklyn Center and a member of the Board of Trustees of the Brooklyn Academy of Music. He was subsequently appointed Vice-President of Long Island University in 1958 and served as a member of the University's Board of Trustees from 1959-1960.
Hester was appointed Dean of the Graduate School of Arts and Science at New York University in 1960 and concurrently served as Executive Dean of Arts and Science and Professor of History. In 1962, Hester assumed the role of University President, which he occupied until his resignation in 1975 to become Rector of the United Nations University.
Related Materials
Records of the Office of the President (Dr. James McNaughton Hester) (RG 3.0.7)
http://dlib.nyu.edu/findingaids/html/archives/hester/
Scope and Contents
The bulk of the James Hester Clippings Collection consists of newspaper and magazine clippings from 1960-1973, New York University (NYU) press releases from 1961-1972, and biographical materials including correspondence with Ralph Nader, selected writings such as reports, proposals and articles, biographical information related to Marquis Who's Who publications and one Association of American Colleges publication, all related to NYU and post-NYU career of James M. Hester. The collection also contains press releases from other institutions related to Hester, a press kit from his 1962 Inauguration as President of NYU and press releases regarding the subsequent role he assumed as Rector of the United Nations University.
College Presidents -- New York (State) -- Biography; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Press releases.; Hester, James M., 1924-; New York University -- History
- Series I: Clippings
  Scope and Contents
  Materials in Series I include newspaper and magazine clippings from 1960-1973 including articles related to student strikes and Hester's reflections on serving ten years as NYU's President.
  - Clippings, Student Strikes, 1911, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Clippings, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Clippings, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Clippings, Jan.-July 1962 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Clippings, Oct.-Dec., 1962 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Clippings, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Clippings, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Clippings, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Clippings, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Clippings, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Clippings, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Clippings, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Clippings, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Clippings, Hester Reflects on 10 Years as NYU President, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Clippings, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Series II: Press Releases
  Materials in Series II include New York University (NYU) press releases from 1961-1972; biographical materials including correspondence with Ralph Nader; selected writings such as reports, proposals and articles; biographical information related to Marquis Who's Who publications; one Association of American Colleges publication; a press kit from Hester's 1962 Inauguration as President of NYU; and press releases regarding the subsequent role Hester assumed as Rector of the United Nations University.
  - Press Releases, Inauguration Proceedings, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Press Releases, Inauguration Press Kit, 25 October 1962 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Press Releases, New York University, 1963-1964 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Press Releases, New York University, 1965-1972 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Press Releases, Other Institutions, 1962-1972 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, Nader, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Selected Writings, 1962-1972 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Misc. Biographical Information, 1961-1962, 1970-1974 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Related Materials, Association of American Colleges, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 15)